<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: agile | jelrik.me]]></title>
  <link href="http://jelrik.me/blog/categories/agile/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jelrik.me/"/>
  <updated>2015-10-17T11:13:16+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://jelrik.me/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jelrik van Hal]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Transform your daily standup]]></title>
    <link href="http://jelrik.me/blog/2015/10/17/transform-your-standup/"/>
    <updated>2015-10-17T13:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://jelrik.me/blog/2015/10/17/transform-your-standup</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>So you&rsquo;re a developer. Of course you&rsquo;re doing SCRUM. Every sprint starts with a planning and ends with a review or demo.
There&rsquo;s a retrospective, some refinement sessions, and of course, your standup (or daily SCRUM). And although you&rsquo;re
following guidelines and have &ldquo;standup questions&rdquo; everyone needs to answer, there&rsquo;s something wrong. The standup takes
forever, <strong>you feel you&rsquo;re wasting time there</strong>. You already know what you&rsquo;re colleagues are up to. Why does that SCRUM
master make you listen to this?</p>

<p>Sounds familiar? It does, right? You&rsquo;re doing the standup wrong. Read on and transform your standup into <strong>the little
ball of energy and focus for the whole team</strong> that it is meant to be.</p>

<p>.. image:: /assets/transform-your-standup/scrum.jpg</p>

<p>.. more</p>

<h2>So, what is it meant to be?</h2>

<p>The first thing that pops to mind when mentioning the standup is &ldquo;tell people what you have been doing and what you will
do today&rdquo;. Or maybe &ldquo;let the scrum master and product owner know how we are doing&rdquo;. While that is undoubtedly very
interesting, it is not what the meeting is about.</p>

<p>The standup is there for team members. The update they present to eachother is a way to <strong>spot problems before they
arise</strong>. A way to <strong>regain focus</strong>. It&rsquo;s not as easy as it sounds but once your team masters the specifics of a
sensible standup, the meeting is a source of information you can use to perfect the team&rsquo;s happiness. And by that, help
the performance of the team improve.</p>

<h2>Symptoms of potential improvement</h2>

<p>The following symptoms could be an indication your standup can do with a little improvement. Before proposing another
approach, I&rsquo;ll try and explain what went wrong in the first place.</p>

<p>Your standup questions</p>

<hr />

<p>&ldquo;What did you do yesterday?&rdquo; and &ldquo;What will you do today?&rdquo; are the standup questions I often come across. The problem
with them is that they stand alone. <strong>They do not in any way relate to the larger body of work</strong> or progress that your
team is trying to get done, such as the sprint goal. They don&rsquo;t even relate to what you said in the standup the day
before.</p>

<p>Your standup is a way for developers to get a feeling of their flow. <strong>Are you well on your way as a team?</strong> Do you see
any current or future problems that you need to tackle as a team? Report what you have been doing in close relation to
what you told everyone you would be doing the day before.</p>

<p>I propose the following standup questions:
1. Did you reach your personal daily goal since the last standup?
2. What will be your personal daily goal until the next standup?
3. What prevents you and your team from reaching your sprint goal?</p>

<p>By explicitly setting a goal and referring back to it the next day, you&rsquo;re making progress measurable, and more
importantly <em>feel-able</em>, for your co-developers. This set of questions basically breaks down the larger sprint goal into
smaller blocks. Not reaching your goal is not failure at all and <strong>you shouldn&rsquo;t be mocked for that</strong>. There are loads
of valid reasons for not getting there. However, noticing that someone did not reach their daily goal can help identify
impediments that are working against you.</p>

<p>Your standup is a status report</p>

<hr />

<p>Closely related to the standup questions discussed above, I often see developers reporting the status of an issue to the
project manager, SCRUM master or product owner. The developers have committed to making the sprint during sprint
planning. Micro-management during a sprint will only create tension between developers and other SCRUM team members,
such as the product owner.</p>

<p>A product owner, SCRUM master, or anyone not explicitly part of the team <strong>needs to place their trust in the
developers</strong>. Your job as a developer is to set your mind to finish an issue. This is a creative process of problem
identification followed by problem solving. No-one can predict up-front how much time that process will take. Not even
you. No, really, you can&rsquo;t.</p>

<p>So how can anyone place trust in a developer that doesn&rsquo;t know when an issue will be finished? Simple. They need to
realize that software engineering is an unpredictable practice. Let them trust you in finishing an issue to your best
capacities <strong>and report to them if there are any problems</strong>. They will then know that the development team does not need
micromanagement. This kind of status report is, however, not what the standup is for.</p>

<p>I propose that, if you walk into problems while fixing or implementing an issue that possibly prevent the team from
reaching their sprint goal, you walk over to the product owner and/or SCRUM master to tell them. Don&rsquo;t wait for the
standup. They will want to know anyway. This saves a lengthy explanation of the problem at hand during standup. Which I
will say once more, is a meeting for developers to get a feeling on their flow as a team.</p>

<p>You are interrupted during your update</p>

<hr />

<p>So, you are telling people what you have been up to, how that relates to your personal daily goal, and the sprint goal
at large. Exactly as described above. You did it all. And still, there&rsquo;s that product owner interrupting you during your
update.</p>

<p>Tell the guy or gal to knock it off. Seriously. Tell them to let you speak. Refer to the trust I point out in the
previous paragraph. No-one should interrupt you.</p>

<p>There are two general reasons why people are interrupting. The first is that they actually have valid questions. In that
case, make sure to finish your standup with a general quick-question round. Don&rsquo;t go into detail. Try to offload the
answering of questions to somewhere outside the standup. But offer everyone the chance to ask these questions.</p>

<p>A second possible reason is that people think of something while you are talking, and they should have been telling this
to the group during their own update.</p>

<p>To solve the latter problem, as well as to help solve the first one, you might introduce a &ldquo;speaking stick&rdquo;, &ldquo;standup
totem&rdquo;, or the like. Find an object that can easily be hold while talking. The one holding the totem is the one doing
the talking. No-one else talks. This is a very explicit and visible way of enforcing the &ldquo;I am talking. Let me.&rdquo; rule,
but it works quite nicely. The one thing to remember is to be very, very strict about it.</p>

<p>People don&rsquo;t come prepared</p>

<hr />

<p>Another observation I made is the high rate of participants attending the standup unprepared. While talking, they are
looking through the SCRUM board for the issues they have been working on, thinking aloud.</p>

<p>This is the simplest of improvements. Define your standup questions (you could use my proposal found above) and prepare
your answers to them. Present your part in a logical and coherent way, while relating to the larger (sprint) goal. This
just saves time and allows for a better understanding of what you are actually trying to say.</p>

<p>Your standup takes place early in the morning</p>

<hr />

<p>This is a tricky one. There is nothing really inherently wrong with having your standup early. It could, however, be an
indication of a deeper problem. The standup doesn&rsquo;t have to be early. The standup doesn&rsquo;t have to be your daily
kick-off, it can easily be held just before or after lunch, or some other convenient time of the day.</p>

<p>When planning your standup, observe the main objectives of the meeting: confidence in the current flow, and focus.
<strong>To maximize the development team&rsquo;s focus, you need your meetings to interrupt as few people as possible from their
focused workflow.</strong></p>

<p>If most of your team enters the office around the same time in the morning, it makes sense to plan your standup at that
moment before everyone gets up to speed for the day.</p>

<p>However, if some people start their workdays at 8AM and others arrive at 10AM, having a 10AM standup breaks the 4 hours
of undisturbed work before lunch for the earlybirds. Planning it just before or after lunch, a moment when focus is
broken anyway, could in that case just make sense.</p>

<p>There is no silver bullet here. Evaluate your team&rsquo;s standup time, find the moment that fits your team. Just make sure
it&rsquo;s the same time, every day.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s an iterative process</p>

<hr />

<p><strong>Like everything in modern software development, your standup format is an iterative process too.</strong> Experiment. Find
your way. Find the team&rsquo;s way. Don&rsquo;t change everything at the same time, people seem not to be very good at handling
large sets of changes at once.</p>

<p>Talk about this with your team. <strong>Try to find out what you and your team members want to get out of the daily
standup.</strong> Define the goal and then find means to achieve that goal.</p>

<p>And if it doesn&rsquo;t work? No problem, no shame, no-ones fault. Change it. Keep the feedback cycle short. It&rsquo;s an iterative
process anyway.</p>

<h2>Symptoms I missed</h2>

<p>This is by no means a full list of symptoms of standups that could do with improvements. These are just situations I run
into. Do you have an example from your workplace? Or do you disagree with solutions I proposed? Please leave a comment
below.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
